<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Karol Kuczmarski's Blog</title><link href="http://xion.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://xion.io/feeds/thoughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://xion.io/</id><updated>2016-04-08T08:32:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>In Microsoft we trust</title><link href="http://xion.io/post/thoughts/in-microsoft-we-trust.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-08T08:32:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Karol Kuczmarski</name></author><id>tag:xion.io,2016-04-08:post/thoughts/in-microsoft-we-trust.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just like many other people, I was following news from the last week&amp;#8217;s
&lt;a href="https://build.microsoft.com/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BUILD&lt;/span&gt; conference&lt;/a&gt; with piqued interest. The ability to run Linux userland programs
on Windows &amp;#8212; including, of course,
&lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com/2016/03/30/be-very-afraid-hell-has-frozen-over-bash-is-coming-to-windows-10/"&gt;bash&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8212;
is something to be excited about. If nothing else, it should dramatically improve Windows support of new programming
languages that seem to pop up all the&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was something else, however, that I couldn&amp;#8217;t help but notice. The reactions of tech communities to this and similar developments focused very frequently on Microsoft&amp;nbsp;itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beloved &amp;#8220;new Microsoft&amp;#8221;,
as &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/4cqm9y/xamarin_becomes_free_and_opensource/d1kjwl8"&gt;some call it&lt;/a&gt;,
embraces open source, supports Linux, and generally does almost a full 180 with their stance on
proprietary vs. free software. The circumstances fit this narrative rather snuggly, too: a new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt; makes a clean break
with the past to pivot the company in this new world ruled by mobile and&amp;nbsp;cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still&amp;#8230; &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;? Even considering how Internet comments are grotesquely exaggerated most of the time, that&amp;#8217;s quite
a declaration. The sentiment is nowhere near isolated either. But it&amp;#8217;s not a question whether this infatuation
has a rational merit, or whether those feelings will eventually turn out to be&amp;nbsp;misplaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is: why does it exist at all? We are talking about a &lt;em&gt;company&lt;/em&gt; here, a for-profit organization.
How can such a language even enter the&amp;nbsp;picture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I realized this is not really a new phenomenon. Quite the opposite: the broad developer community seems to
always need a company to champion its core values. Nowadays, we&amp;#8217;re simply trying to find someone new
to carry the&amp;nbsp;standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Because we feel that our old heroes have forsaken&amp;nbsp;us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hall of past&amp;nbsp;fame&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take &lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt; for example. Once a darling of the open source community, it&amp;#8217;s been suffering sharp criticism
for many months now. Rightfully or not, many people aren&amp;#8217;t exactly excited &amp;#8212; to put it mildly &amp;#8212; about changes to
the &lt;a href="https://github.com/blog/2146-organizations-can-now-block-abusive-users"&gt;policy&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://github.com/blog/2039-adopting-the-open-code-of-conduct"&gt;atmosphere&lt;/a&gt; at GitHub,
typified by the ill-fated &lt;a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/githubs-ceo-ditches-meritocracy-rug-2014-1"&gt;meritocracy rug&lt;/a&gt;.
The widely backed and long standing &lt;a href="https://github.com/dear-github/dear-github"&gt;plea for a few critical features&lt;/a&gt;
has only recently stopped falling on deaf ears. And in the background, there are always concerns about GitHub simply
&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10823128"&gt;becoming too big&lt;/a&gt;, and exterting too much control over
the open source&amp;nbsp;ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nota bene&lt;/em&gt;, the very same ecosystem it had once been lauded for&amp;nbsp;nurturing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the other flagship tech companies, &lt;strong&gt;Apple&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Facebook&lt;/strong&gt; have never garnered much good will. Sure, they are
recognized for the pure utilitarian value of hardware they produce; or convenience, broad applicability, and stability
of APIs they offer. Facebook may be scoring some additional points for trying to
&lt;a href="https://facebook.github.io/react/"&gt;sort out&lt;/a&gt; the mess of frontend development, but many say it&amp;#8217;s
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@ericclemmons/javascript-fatigue-48d4011b6fc4#.j740brod8"&gt;not doing anybody any favors&lt;/a&gt;.
Neither company is easy to portray as a paragon of openness, though, and it&amp;#8217;s probably easier to argue
&lt;a href="http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/apples-closed-ecosystem-threatening-derail-technological-revolution-1535944"&gt;the exact opposite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there is &lt;strong&gt;Google&lt;/strong&gt;, of course&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Some time in the past few years, a palpable shift occurred in how
the company is perceived by the techie crowd. It&amp;#8217;s difficult to pinpoint the exact pivotal moment, and the
&lt;a href="https://googleblog.blogspot.com.au/2013/03/a-second-spring-of-cleaning.html"&gt;one event that leaps to attention&lt;/a&gt;
doesn&amp;#8217;t seem sufficient to explain it. But the tone has been set,
allowing &lt;a href="http://google-opensource.blogspot.com/2015/03/farewell-to-google-code.html"&gt;news&lt;/a&gt; to be
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/2yt73v/google_to_close_google_code_open_source_project/cpdb6xs"&gt;molded&lt;/a&gt;
to fit it. Add this to the usual backdrop of complaints about the
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/2ll864/my_horrible_google_interview_experience/"&gt;onerous&lt;/a&gt;
interview process and general fearmongering, and the picture doesn&amp;#8217;t look very&amp;nbsp;bright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Shades of&amp;nbsp;grey&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No similar woes seem to have been plaguing Microsoft as of late, even though their record of recent &amp;#8220;unwholesome&amp;#8221; deeds
isn&amp;#8217;t exactly
&lt;a href="http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/news/2447177/updategate-windows-10-is-resetting-default-apps-back-to-microsoft-stock"&gt;clean&lt;/a&gt;
either. Does it mean they are indeed the most fitting candidate for a (new) enterprise ally of the hacker&amp;nbsp;community?&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe we can finally recognize the whole notion as the utterly silly concept it actually is. Hard to shake though
it be, this quasi-Manicheic mentality of assigning labels of virtue or sin is, at best, a naive idealism. At worst,
it&amp;#8217;s a peculiar kind of harmful partisanship that technologists are particularly susceptible to. You may recognize it
as something that has a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Editor_war"&gt;very long tradition&lt;/a&gt; in the hacker&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it doesn&amp;#8217;t mean it&amp;#8217;s a tradition worth&amp;nbsp;keeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no illusions I will be attributed any objectivity, but it bears mentioning
&lt;a href="http://xion.io/page/about.html"&gt;again&lt;/a&gt; that nothing I say here is representative of anything but my own opinions.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Microsoft"></category><category term="Windows"></category><category term="GitHub"></category><category term="Apple"></category><category term="Facebook"></category><category term="Google"></category><category term="tech culture"></category></entry></feed>